<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short and true discourse for satisfying all those vvho not knovving the truth, speake indiscreetly of hir most excellent Maiestie, of the Lord Willughby Gouernour of hir Maiesties succours in the vnited prouinces of the Low countries, and of all the English nation: by occasion of a strange placcat of the 17. of April 1589. the new stile, put foorth by certaine particular persons (as is said) vnder the name of the General States of those vnited prouinces. By which discourse, euery one is praied and required to speake well and honorably of th'actions of those estates generall lawfully assembled. Together with an extraict of the authentique euidences and proofes for the chiefe poincts of this discourse, whereunto they are directed by respectiue quotation of page and line</title>
            <author>Willoughby de Eresby, Peregrine Bertie, Baron, 1555-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841203</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841203</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 337:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short and true discourse for satisfying all those vvho not knovving the truth, speake indiscreetly of hir most excellent Maiestie, of the Lord Willughby Gouernour of hir Maiesties succours in the vnited prouinces of the Low countries, and of all the English nation: by occasion of a strange placcat of the 17. of April 1589. the new stile, put foorth by certaine particular persons (as is said) vnder the name of the General States of those vnited prouinces. By which discourse, euery one is praied and required to speake well and honorably of th'actions of those estates generall lawfully assembled. Together with an extraict of the authentique euidences and proofes for the chiefe poincts of this discourse, whereunto they are directed by respectiue quotation of page and line</title>
                  <author>Willoughby de Eresby, Peregrine Bertie, Baron, 1555-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Peregrine Bertie, Baron Willoughby de Eresby.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5766:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT AND TRVE DISCOVRSE FOR SATISFYING ALL THOSE VVHO NOT KNOVVING THE truth, ſpeake indiſcreetly of hir moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, of the Lord Willughby Gouernour of hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſuccours in the vnited Prouinces of the Low countries, and of all the Engliſh nation: by occaſion of a ſtrange placcat of the 17. of April 1589. the new ſtile, put foorth by certaine particular perſons (as is ſaid) vnder the name of the Generall States of thoſe vnited Prouinces. By which diſcourſe, euery one is praied and required to ſpeake well and Honorably of th'actions of thoſe Eſtates generall lawfully aſſembled. Together with An Extraict of the authentique euidences and proofes for the chiefe poincts of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, whereunto they are directed by reſpectiue quotation of page and Line. 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:5766:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5766:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT DISCOVRSE TOVCHING the ſiege before Gertrudenbergh, and the towne loſt by reaſon thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is holden a point of ſome perilous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, to breede grudging in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant toward his maſter. This is principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuented by that Scripture, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs to detain the wage of him whom we ſet on worke. But as the rules of holy Scriptures are not preciſely kept in priuate matters, through mans corruption and otherwiſe: euen ſo falleth it out in more publike affaires, as for example, in the caſe of Brakeley fortreſſe, and of the townes of Heuſden and Gertrudenbergh, where the men of warre in garriſon for the general Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces in the Low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, by want of pay and other miſſeintrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>February, March, 1588</label> about February and March 1588. fell ſo farre more and more miſcontent, as notwithſtanding the broyle of Brakeley quenched by Counte Hohenloes ſiege, &amp; that of Heuſden redeemed by a great ſumme of mony for pay already farre runne: yet ſtill that of Gertrudenbergh ſeemed deſperat, the garriſon there refuſing once to deale either with generall or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular States, or with Count Maurice of Naſſau, no more then with Count Hohenlo their laſt gouernor, as is declared by the placcard it ſelfe and many other proofes. But forſomuch as this placcard ſpecifieth in plaine language that thoſe ſoldiours couered theſe their dealings vnder her Maieſties name, taking ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alſo further occaſion by ſome letters and perſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5766:3"/> ſent to them from the Lord Willughby Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour generall &amp;c. And forſomuch as ſome malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and enuious at her Maieſties greatneſſe, and at the weale and repoſe of her ſubiectes &amp; good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, are not aſhamed to publiſh this: that, So as men vſe the name of her Maieſtie and of her miniſters, it is tollerated without paine and chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do euill in thoſe prouinces, as if her Maieſtie and miniſters made way to wickednes: we muſt call thoſe euill tounged men to ſome better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the roiall affection and zeale wherewith her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie proceedeth, in fauouring &amp; aſſiſting at al needs and ſeaſons, by all meanes that God putteth in her princely hands, thoſe prouinces &amp; Eſtates repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoueraingty there. To beginne with the warres in time of the late prince of Orenge of honorable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, you ſhall find in the contract made by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Edward Dier for her Maieſtie, what aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was accorded to that prince and country: beſides that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery porte of her kingdom, gaue free paſſage out &amp; in to all ſuch as aſſiſted or fauoured him. It is well knowne how the Marqueſſe of Haurech being ſent 1578. by the States general, obteined of the Queene great ſummes of mony in preſt, which are not yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. And if we ſhall but only name the latter wars, ſince Braba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; Flanders loſt, &amp; ſince the death of the duke of Aniou, &amp; of the Prince of Ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, I ſay ſince Antwerpe loſt, &amp; the ſuccourleſſe negotiation with the French king broken of, when all things ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly wauered in thoſe prouinces: it will moſt cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare with what cheerefulneſſe hir Maieſtie not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5766:3"/> ſparing hir Nobilitie, imployed all meanes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thoſe countries and States. All this with a moſt ſincere and heroical mind, not ſo much as accepting the offers to hir made of thoſe countries. So farre is hir Maieſtie from ſuffering or wittingly and willingly winking at ſuch euils in thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, whoſe gratious endeuour hath bin with no leſſe care of hir neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in all their extremities then of hir owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. But going thus ſlyly about to obſcure hir moſt high &amp; honorable actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you barke at the ful Moone or rather ſeeke to ſhadow the ſunne, whoſe brightnes breaketh foorth through all cloudes and is glorious in heauen and earth. Smaller ſtarres perhaps, ſuch as Barons and Lords, though their honor ſhineth by hir ſoueraigne light, yet may they ſeeme to ſuffer ſome darkneſſe by theſe cloudie oppoſitions or miſts rather ſmoking out of diches, except they labor ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in declaration of their owne cleereneſſe.</p>
            <p>This maketh the Lord Willughby Gouernour generall of hir Maieſties ſuccours in thoſe prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to ſay in defence of his honour: Firſt, that this placcard, as in many things elſe, ſo affirming him to haue ſought by letters and meſſengers, to maintaine them of Gertrudenbergh in mutine, doth notably forge and counterfait. For howſoeuer it were free &amp; lawfull for him to ſend thither, hir Maieſtie and thoſe prouinces being by vertue of precedent contract friends to friends, &amp; enemies to enemies: vpon what reaſon or ground could he ſend thither. Sith at the generall States inſtance to hir Maieſtie, he had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die charge and commandement from his ſoueraigne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5766:4"/> Miſtreſſe to accompliſh their deſires, for Narden, Medenblicke, La Vere, and Armude, according as he performed the ſame one after an other to their full and whole contentment, and to the ſtopping of theſe wicked mouthes in this behalfe, that ſpeake thus ſlanderouſly of the Lord Willughby. For like as his obedience and faithfull ſeruice is apparant in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling th'affaires of theſe foure places: ſo certaine and manifeſt it is, that for the towne of Gertrudenbergh, he neuer conceiued nor intended to do ought that might diſpleaſe hir Maieſtie and the States, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme hazard to his wife, children, and all ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and meanes as by Gods mercy vnder hir bleſſed gouuernment he enioyeth in England. What if that garriſon would treat with none ſaue with the Lord Willughby on hir Maieſties behalfe? Should that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd to his diſhonour, and not much rather to the encreaſe of hir Maieſties greatneſſe, who by Gods grace winneth ſuch reputation among theſe ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſoldiours, that albeit they neuer reaped other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit or reward from hir, then by vertue of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracie of treatie with thoſe prouinces: yet they chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed rather to hold that towne in hir Maieſties name vnto the generalitie then to rendre to th'enemy, though they alledged many occaſions of ſuch rendre giuen them, which they did afterward more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly diſcourſe in writing, and which ſhalbe more largely ſpoken of hereafter. If then there be any ſpice of diſhonor in this action, it muſt light on them, who by diſorder, careleſnes, and fault of due pay to that garriſon, ſuffered things there to runne to that vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5766:4"/> that to ſaue the place, theſe diſorders and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions ſuffered and wrought by them could not be redreſſed but by th'autoritie charge, expence, and great trauell of hir Maieſties ſeruants. Had the Lord Willughby caried this actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his owne proper au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, in deed, he ſhould hardly haue anſwered it to his ſoueraigne Miſtreſſe and the States, as hauing exceeded his commiſſion and therefore to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned for ambitious, and not content with his owne charge. But it is farre otherwiſe as the very placcard ſheweth. For being many times required and prayed aſwell by the generall States, the councell of Eſtate, Conte Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the States of Holland, as alſo by the Magiſtrat of Dordrecht, to ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be imployed about appeaſing Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, the Lord Willughby neuertheleſſe to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues that might inſinuat any pretence in hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, for other townes then compriſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract (a thing broadly and lewdly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among them the laſt yeare) did ſtill put ouer this buſineſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as they that had good meanes to worke this by the going betweene of the Magiſtrate of Dort, next neighbour to Gertrudenbergh, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>April</label> and following his owne affaires and charge all March and Aprill, &amp; principally the reſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a councel of Eſtate, which had long time ceaſſed, and th'appointment of Medenblick and Narden, he euer more excuſed him ſelfe as long as he might. And ſurely he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued his excuſes both for the former reaſons, and alſo for. that being come from the quieting of Medenblicke, God viſited him at Haghe with a long ſickneſſe, had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5766:5"/> not the Magiſtrate of Dort vtterly giuen ouer the matter, without effecting any thing according to th'act of authoriſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them giuen 7. Aprilis afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and therupon the Lord Willughby againe moſt earneſtly ſollicited euen by Counte Hohenlo, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by his letters the laſt of the ſame Aprill and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letters afterward, requiring that he would do his beſt for ſome appointment with Gertrudenbergh: forſomuch as (ſaid he) we perceiue no other meanes left, the garriſon there hauing ſignified by their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the 20. and the Magiſtrate of Dort by theirs of the 28 of the ſame Aprill, that the ſoldiours of Gertrudenbergh would treate with none, but with the Lord Willughby in hir Maieſties name. This was th'occaſion that at laſt his Lordſhip hauing atchieued the States deſire at Medenblick and Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, being as loth to faile in any parte of his ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour for preſeruation alſo of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, a towne ſo greatly importing the prouince of Holland &amp; the generalitie, as they had remonſtrated many times to him, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>May</label> he tooke his iourney without any promiſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the world about the 6. of May toward Dort, to aduiſe with the Magiſtrate there, how this ſtirre of Gertrudenbergh might be quieted. According to aduiſe there, he aduertiſed the garriſon of Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh the 7. following, that he was there arriued wiſhing them to ſend deputies according to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſafe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct, which his Lordſhip ſent them. But that garriſon ſtanding vpon excuſe for ſending depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and beſeeching the ſame Lord Baron to come to them in perſon, his Lordſhip becauſe he would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5766:5"/> not farther endaunger thoſe affaires, being yet ſo ſmally come on, ſent thither Sir Iohn Wingfield knight, M. Thomas Wilford Sergeant maior of the Engliſh, &amp; George Gilpin ſecretarie of Eſtate there, accompanied with M. Ioos Menin counſailor pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner of Dort, &amp; Dirick Geerbrantſen Stoop, who wrought in ſuch ſort with them of Gertrudenbergh, as they ſent deputies to Dort the 9. of May, who preſently vpon their arriuall exhibited to the Lord Willughby, a certaine diſcourſe ſigned and ſealed, conteining the reaſons of their miſcontentment, &amp; therewithall, certaine articles demaunding ſecurity to themſelues for any thing doone in this alteration. Vpon which articles of aſſurance after good delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and communication firſt had with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of Dort, certaine points were apoſtilled, but yet without agreeing any thing definitiuely to that garriſon, which might be interpreted preiudiciall, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the generall of the country, or the particular of Holland: yea, quite to the contrary, his Lordſhip ſharply by word and writing blamed their vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be paid from hir Maieſtie, to whom hitherto they had done no particular ſeruice. Their deputies ſtood herevpon, that forſomuch as theſe matters could not determine at Dort, it would pleaſe the Lord Willughby to come perſonally to Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh, that ſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place all things might take better end, whereunto his Lordſhip hauing partly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented with the Magiſtrats aduiſe of Dort, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 13. of May, with intention yet not to enter the towne of Gertrudenbergh, but lying in his boate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5766:6"/> before the towne to negociat from out of his boate with the garriſon. But by occaſion of a treaſon the next night before diſcouered, which had bene prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by Captaine Fournet and Marke Albanois, both which ſuffered therefore afterward, the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lugh by was driuen to enter the towne that very day, &amp; that without hoſtages or any other aſſurance, ſaue the ſigned writing of the Deputies of Dort and Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudenbergh, or elſe the towne was to fall in more danger then euer before.</p>
            <p>If two moneths and more before this time, the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of this garriſon for want of pay, had changed their Colours tearing and renting their Cornets, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and Banderols from their lances and ſtandarts, as this placcard rehearſeth, we leaue it to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all men, yea of theſe euill ſpeakers, and euen of theſe which did impertinently reproch a certaine promiſe neuer thought of, together with th'apoſtilles of the ninth of May, we leaue it I ſay to all good conſideration, whether the Lorde Willughby might not iuſtly doubt of his owne ſafety, being now in the handes of a ſort of warlike malcontents, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one farthing to content them. But being taught by experience in ſuch caſes to make vertue of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, his Lordſhip caried himſelfe ſo with them, as by Gods grace and th'aſſiſtance of the Deputies of Dordrecht he calmed their choler, and brought them ſo farre on, as to yeeld their demand in writing the foureteenth of May, which was one and thirtie moneths pay, releaſing all ſurplus.</p>
            <p>They inſiſted vpon ready mony, but were brought
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5766:6"/> by the Lord Willughby, yet ſo farre further on as to giue one moneths day: notwithſtanding their altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had already continued two moneths. About which matter his Lordſhip not hauing other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſaue to heare and vnderſtand, after he had required them to hold all good and ſoldiour like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, while the States &amp; Count Maurice of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau being aduertiſed might reſolue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, he left with them at their requeſt Sir Iohn Wingfeld for entertainement of ſome better order: &amp; ſo departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gertrudenbergh the 15. of May, without promiſe of one halfe penie to them. What a ſtrange thing is this then, that together with theſe occurrents ſhould come to be alleaged the apoſtilles of the 9. of May, as if by them had growen ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to the countrie, ſith all that paſſed at Dort was but to make way to theſe affaires, &amp; to the Lord Willughbies iourney toward Gertrudenbergh, and ſith that by the apoſtilles nothing was to that garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon agreed definitiuely, but the finall accord concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> differred more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two moneths, that is to ſay, till the 26. and 27. of Iulie following, whereof the States and Count Maurice of Naſſau hauing ſigned that contract are not ignorant. What ſhall we ſay to theſe calumnies? No nouelty, a thing well knowne to the whole world, that is that the Lord Willughby being entreated to mediat in this extreme neceſſitie, and at his owne charge to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare an appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of that alteration, which hapned through want of pay and other euill vſage, is now requited with this ingratitude and diſacknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5766:7"/> together with a practiſe of perſuading lies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him to the people, ſpecially in that point of th'apoſtilles by which I ſay, it is notorious that no damage could come to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try nor to any perſon in particular. For Count Maurice of Naſſau being aduertiſed of all this by the Secretary of Eſtate Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orge Gilpin, thanked the Lord Willughby therefore by expreſſe letters of the 11. of that moneth.</p>
            <p>The reſt is in ſubſtaunce, that the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby after his departure from Gertrudenbergh the 15. of this moneth, aduertiſing the States and Count Maurice of Naſſau, of the ſoldiors foreſaid demaund and of the time which by his meanes they gaue for ſatisfaction, he went to Walckerland at their inſtance alſo, ſpecially of the States of Zeland, for to appoint th'affaires of Vere &amp; Armude, which townes but ſpecially Vere, the States of the country and Count Maurice of Naſſau did hold as good as beſieged. This Zeland buſines at the firſt ſeemed to promiſe ſpeedy diſpatch. But at this very time Oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d finding it ſelfe threatned with ſiege by th'enemy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the L. Willughby thither: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>June</label> ſo was the contract of Vere ſtaied till about the 20. of Iune. Hauing atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe things to the great contentment of the States of Zeland and of Count Maurice of Naſſau, the Lord Willugh by hir Maieſties generall ſailed vp to Holland to the counſaile of Eſtate, where being arriued, it was told him that Gertrudenbergh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſtood in the ſame plight he left them at his going downe to Zela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or rather in worſe, by reaſon the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours now refuſed the reckonings offred to them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5766:7"/> without alſo giuing eare or any reuerence at all to Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maurices letters of the 29. of May in his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips abſence, written to put them in mind how the towne of Gertrudenbergh apperteined to his late Lord &amp; father, after whoſe death he was coheire with his brethren and ſiſters who had no way offended the garriſon there: and that therefore he deſired to ſend commiſſioners to treat with them vpon their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the States generall &amp; they of Holland particularly, renewed their earneſt requeſt for his Lordſhips emploiment in this appointment of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudenbergh: becauſe, they ſaid, they knew no other remedy. To which end alſo Count Maurice of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau gaue him autentike copies of two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions, the one diſpatched by the States generall the 2. of Iune, the other by the States of Holland the 3. of the ſame, pourporting that Count Maurice as Gouernour of Holland &amp; proprietary of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, ſhuld treat with them of that towne iointly with the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby or by meanes of his Lordſhip onely: with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainct neuertheleſſe that by whatſoeuer appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be made, the towne muſt not be ſeparated fro the prouince of Holland, according as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion conteineth. The Lord Willughby ſeing him ſelfe this preſſed on euery ſide, ouercome with the deſire which he knoweth to be in hir Maieſtie his Miſtreſſe, who taketh nothing more to hart then to defend al thoſe prouinces with euery of their townes and places, and greatly caried in his owne affection to do all good office and pleaſures to the States and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5766:8"/> Count Maurice of Naſſau, according as already he manifeſted the ſame by appointing and bringing home into their duotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the towns of Medenblick and Narden in Holland, and of Vere and Armude in Zeland, he yeelded to aſſiſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing of this appointment according to thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions. And this did he the rather moued by letters of the 10. of Iune to Count Maurice of Naſſau from S. Iohn Wingfield knight, conteining that the ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours there had threatned that they would quickly find a ſoueraigne Prince, ſith the Queene of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d would neither take them into protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor procure aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their perſons &amp; pay: beſides other aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements by letters of the 19. of this moneth, to his Lordſhip fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Magiſtrat of Dort, how the ſoldiers of that garriſon began to ſpeake of hearkening to the enimy, &amp; of a purpoſe to receiue the enimies letters whenſoeuer they ſhould be ſent, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that hard before they had hanged vp Captein Fournet &amp; the Albanois with others for a particular treaſon. So then to preuent theſe apparant dangers and vpon theſe their earneſt inſtances the Lord Willughby accompanied Count Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of the States, hauing commiſſion of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and twentith of Iune, from the States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to promiſe to that garriſon 20. moneths pay or two hundred thouſand florins. Comming thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gertrudenbergh to appeaſe this alteration they proceeded ſo farre remaining ſtill in their boates, as diuers times offer of the ſaid ſumme was made to the deputies of the garriſon the 28. of this moneth. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5766:8"/> the day following, the Lord Willughby ſeing them refuſe this offer and to ſtand obſtinatly vpon foure &amp; twentie moneths pay as appeeres by their writing: he could not but maruaile with ſome diſdaine, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſent a ſharpe letter into the garriſon, and yet not ſo content, he declared by word to Count Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau, and the States deputies there, and to them of Dort, that for his particular he held it beſt ſith the ſoldiours ſtood ſo obſtinate, rather to aſſaile the towne by force then to burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prouinces with ſuch a ſumme. Or elſe that if in further treaty with them they would articulate, that his Lordſhip with his gard might enter the towne for conduct of the mony to be paid them, that he would vpon that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent do his beſt to bring the towne into the Countes hands as owner thereof.</p>
            <p>This propoſition throughly deliberated in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, it was anſwered by the Count and all the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that (notwithſtanding th'enemy had then no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at hand that might induce the garriſon to change party) yet to attend th'euent of the forcible attempt were too too hazardous, and to promiſe any more they wanted commiſſion. Whereuppon the ſaid Lords, Count, Lord Willughby and deputies of the States, departed from the flote before Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, and went to the Haghe without any finall compoſition of this alteration. Lo here that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for which ſome ſlanderers do find fault with hir Maieſties Lord Lieutenant Generall, as if neither remembring the ten thouſand da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers which he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcaped within that towne in May laſt, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5766:9"/> th'extreme perils now alſo immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there, he would moſt vnaduiſedly preſume to promiſe by him ſelfe alone to render that towne, and therupon make ſir Iohn Wingfield to giue his hand to Count Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau, which ſelfe ſame towne all the vnited Prouinces thought not good to ſet vpon by force, but rather by their departure ſeemed to abandon, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his Lordſhip then promiſed his beſt offices to bring it about to their deſire, if they had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to follow his aduiſe. In which emploiment he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him ſelfe with the very ſame affection to do pleaſure and ſeruice to Count Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the States, as he had done in the other foure townes which they preſently held in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their whole contentement.<note place="margin">Meden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicke. Narden. La Vere. Armude.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeake truly and certainly of theſe occurrents, we muſt ſtay vpon the manage of euery affaire as it paſſed from day to day, in which behalfe he that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſigned the placcard either erreth of miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or elſe miſreporteth of malice. An abuſe offered to none ſomuch as to his owne Maiſters, blindfolding their eies as if they ſaw not that which all the world ſeeth: and therfore, forſooth, men muſt vpon great paine be forbidden to ſay that which is apparantly true, that is, That certaine particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were the very cauſe of that towne loſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne fault irreparable, will needes colour their excuſe by the Lord Willughby. And this is not their firſt wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g done him in his honor. For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was Gouernour of Berghes op Zoom, they ſhamed not to calumniat his actions as if he had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5766:9"/> had ſome ſiniſtre drift againſt that towne, which his Lordſhip held alwaies very deere. <note place="margin">Berghes op Zoom defended.</note> But that this their imagination was a falſe lie, fell out euident, when with the perill of his life (all glory be to God) the towne was mainteined againſt a roiall army of the enemy.</p>
            <p>To proceed with the towne of Gertrudenbergh, it makes well for our purpoſe to ſhew how the ſame towne was yet further preſerued, though as good as giuen ouer by the retraict of Count Maurice and the States as aforeſaid, as appeeres by the daily handling of thoſe matters. You muſt vnderſtand that after the States generall, the counſaile of Eſtate, Count Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau, and the States of Holland had better waighed this matter in counſell at the Haghe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>July</label> the L. Willughby was againe required in full counſel the 9. of Iuly, to ſend Richard Allen an Engliſh Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (which his Lordſhip did) togither with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie George Matrut, to declare to the garriſon at Gertrudenbergh, that within fewe daies they ſhould haue their demaund, and that in the meane while they ſhould beare themſelues in all fidelity and good diſcipline. And forſomuch as in this Interim the ſtate of Gertrudenbergh was in great wauering, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon might enſue an vtter breach without fit reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prouided, it was thought good that the deputies of the generall States, Count Maurice of Naſſau, the Lord Willughby, the deputies of Holland and of Dort for their particular, ſhould vpon the 24. fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, be all before the towne of Gertrudenbergh, where came to them into their boates the deputies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5766:10"/> of that garriſon, with certaine points &amp; articles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a finall accord and their owne aſſurance. Which being conſidered in counſell were finally ſet downe for agreed the 26. following, and ſigned by Count Maurice of Naſſau as proprietary of that towne and Gouernour of Holland, and by the Lord Willughby for hir Maieſty. For, as for the States you vnderſtand already that the garriſon would not once treat with them. Now whereas in the ſecond apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille vpon there foreſaid article was compriſed, that the horſemen in the garriſon ſhould be made into one Cornet of 100. lances, and 50. carrabines onely, and their footemen into one Enſigne of 150. and no more, ſo as the reſidue might range themſelues vnder the companies at hir Maieſties charge in Berghen or otherwhere, the whole garriſon being aduertiſed thereof by their deputies, found themſelues greatly intereſſed, and ſetting forth the 27. of Iuly following their griefes and difficulties, declared that they neuer meant to be ſeperated one from an other, for which purpoſe they had condicioned in their ſecond article that they might retaine their garriſon, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that the halfe of their ſoldiors could not be ordred vnder one Cornet and one Enſigne, and that alſo the ſame ſhould be to them great charge and expenſe to go ſeeke ſeruice in an other garriſon. Which point Count Maurice and the States finding hard to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, without being vpon the place among the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, eſpecially their number being yet vnknowne, they left all to the Lord Willughbies diſcretion, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thereof to the ſoldiours an act ſigned by the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5766:10"/> Count and iointly by the Lord Willughby at th'in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the States. Here is the concluſion of finall treaty with them of Gertrudenbergh vntill the very day, made in the boates before the towne.</p>
            <p>Now for th'execution of this treaty you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the ſoldiours being ſomewhat better contented with this laſt apoſtill, the Lord Willugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by went his way from the flote toward Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, at th'inſtance of Count Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the States, and according to the ſecond article of the treaty: where after hoſtages deliuered aſwell on the part of the Magiſtrat as of the garriſon there, his Lordſhip entred but very reaſonably attended, taking immediatly ſuch order with that forlorne ſtate, that vpon the 28 of this moneth, commiſſaries Orſemall, Paraſis and Matrut, deputed thereto by the Count &amp; the States, began to make paiment. And albeit the Lord Willughby might well haue ſought the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of that towne for him ſelfe, or in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for ſir Iohn Wingfield according to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent of the treaty, articul. 3. yet to cleere him of all ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſwell for his owne part (being highly contented with the Honor hir Maieſtie vouchſaueth him) as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for ſir Iohn Wingfield his neere allie: his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip did by letters of the 28. of that moneth to the counſell of State, which had commiſſion to gouerne the prouinces, beſeech them and that vnfainedly that they would beſtow that gouernment on Colonell Sche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k, who had ſued for it. This done, the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby forthwith euen the ſelfe ſame day aduertiſed Count Maurice of Naſſau, who was then gone from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5766:11"/> the flote to Dort, that to reduce and redreſſe thoſe men of warre into conuenient order (which thing yet the very next day before was reſolutely left to the Lord Willughbies diſcretion in regard of thoſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties before moued by the garriſon) there were no other way but to content them by making one Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of 200 lances, and one of 100 Carrabines: one company of foote of 200. one other of 150. which thing though his Lordſhip had already, as is before ſaid, authority by diſcretion to do, yet did he write that he would not do it without firſt knowing the Countes aduiſe, according as alſo he neuer attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any thing in the world about reducing and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of theſe men of warre till firſt and formoſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued two of his letters, conteining his aduiſe before imparted with the deputies of the States firſt at Dort then at Haghe. But ſo ſoone as his Lordſhip had receiued thoſe letters he ſet on hand to reforme &amp; reduce thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies, as the neceſſity, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſeruice, his owne Honor and the holding of that treaty required: yet ſtill according to the Counts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, as before ſaid, conteining a generall clauſe that his Lordſhip might diſpoſe of things as appeeres by th'originalles of 28 and 30 of this moneth. Things being ſo farre on, to finiſh likewiſe the reſt, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, according to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d article of the treaty, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the garriſon the draught of an oth to be taken by them, in ſuch maner and forme as they of hir Maieſties ſuccours had done, that is to ſay, to the States generall &amp;c. euen as the commiſſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had ſet it downe. The ſoldiours hearing but the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5766:11"/> name of the States generall, cried hand ouer head tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuouſly that they had not contracted with the States, neither would they in any ſort ſweare to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Lord Willughby perceiuing that to auoid one difficulty was to fall into an other, finding himſelfe in ſome perplexity as being their alone, not aſſiſted by any of that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, was forced to alter the draught of the oth by omitting the name of States generall: becauſe otherwiſe the mony already paid and to pay being within the towne had bene vtterly loſt, beſides all this negotiation ouerthrowne and his Lordſhips perſon to come in exceeding danger. Yet would not he paſſe further herein, finding the ſoldiours reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly well ſatisfied by putting out the names of the States generall, till he ſent immediatly both the othes drawne as they were to Count Maurice of Naſſau, declaring to him that as by the firſt it was impoſſible to quiet thoſe men of warre, ſo by the ſecond their was good likelihood they might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented. Count Maurice wrote backe by expreſſe letters of the laſt of Iuly that he allowed well of this alteration: ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo ioinctly with the States of Holland to his Lordſhip, that they found it not good to giue the gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gertrudenbergh to Colonel Schenk. Hereupon the Lord Willughby went on, giuing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for that which remained, that ſo the whole pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being once made as equally and as much for the countries profit as was poſſible, the foreſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries being daily therein occupied, his Lordſhip then might grow to finiſh that buſineſſe aſwell for reforming the companies as for giuing their oth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5766:12"/> to thoſe ample commiſſions which alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy his Lordſhip had. The reſt ſeemed of ready diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch. But the mony not being ready, and if it had beene ready, yet not being ſufficient to pay the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours (as the commiſſaries appointed for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can well witneſſe at this day) the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby was faine to aduertiſe Count Maurice of Naſſau, the counſell of Eſtate, the States of Holland and the Magiſtrat of Dort reſpectiuely, to th'end that they might preſently make prouiſion for it, as by his Lordſhips letters of the 2.3.5. &amp; 6. of Auguſt folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appeareth. Count Maurice firſt communicating this with the States, anſwered that the mony was not yet all leuied, earneſtly deſiring the L. Willughby to deale with the Magiſtrat of Gertrudenbergh &amp; Dort to take vp that which wanted, and the States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land would aſſume and vndertake to repay it. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt according to letters to him thereof, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip performed with ſuch dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as the whole pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being quickly made, he proceeded according to his former co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to redreſſe the companies, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to take that very oth which (once againe I ſay it) Count Maurice of Naſſau had not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, but therewithall had ſent the garriſon a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral pardon, which was to them vpon th'inſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered according to the firſt article of the treaty,</p>
            <p>This is the plaine courſe and very true cariage of theſe affaires, ſo to be proued by al &amp; euery th'inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, commiſſions, letters &amp; warrants before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as they are yet exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be ſeene, and for more plaine euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce are extracted in th'end. What a foule placcat then is this, publiſhing to the world againſt al
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5766:12"/> truth, that forſooth the Lord Willughby had redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies as him ſelfe liſted, giuing them an oth to their liking vpon his owne head. But his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions &amp; ſincere actions are ſo euident to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as by allegation of them the people themſelues may eaſily iudge the truth, &amp; we neede ſpeake therof no more. Yet thus much more then neede, that ouer &amp; beſides all the particular ordonances &amp; warrants already ſpoken of, according to which his Lordſhip gouerned him ſelf, he hath more ouer to ſhew an act of thankeſgeuings for all his ſincere actions, which Count Maurice of Naſſau and the States of Holland iointly gaue him before his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that towne: a thing alone that may mainteine his Honor &amp; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with all the world. And that yet ſo much the more, becauſe in the concluſion of the ſame act, the Count and States do confeſſe and ſay, as by other the like they had done, that the Lord Willughby was emploied in appeaſing this altered towne of Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh at their great inſtance and earneſt ſute, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that hir Maieſtie of England (ſo are the words of the act) wil take it in very good part, becauſe ſay they, by this his imploiment the prouince of Holland and conſequently all the countries had receiued a very principall benefit. The Lord Willughby finding him ſelfe this kindly thanked by this act, and conſidering how Count Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land had preferred S. Iohn Wingfield (though yet it were no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the treaty) before Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel Schenck, in the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh: he grew deſirous to requite courteſie with courteſie.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5766:13"/> Whereupon, voluntarily, franckly, and to ſhew that he neuer affected that gouernment neither for him ſelfe nor any other (for as for ſir Iohn Wingfield he was there eſtabliſhed by Count Maurice) he then &amp; not before, made promiſe vnder his hand, in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, this, that forſomuch as he had beene forced to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle in this affaire, and to enter the towne for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing th'alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, &amp; that God of his goodnes had ſo bleſſed his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to paſſe, that for all this he would pretend nothing for himſelfe in the towne, but euer would be ready, as far as were in his power, to reſtore it to Count Maurice of Naſſau: ſo as againe the Count would performe &amp; hold what was promiſed to the ſoldiours there, for conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their liues, wiues and children, according to that which was alſo hir Maieſties deſire. Here appeeres ſufficiently that Count Maurice of Naſſau had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the garriſon a former promiſe, by the precede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t contract, the promiſe of the Lord Willughby ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing relation to a promiſe formerly made to the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, as the very letter of his promiſe plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Let the world iudge how honeſtly theſe men deale in giuing the people to vnderſtand againſt all truth, that the promiſe made by the Lord Willugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhould go before the treaty with Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, the words, I ſay, of this promiſe being ſo cleere to the contrary, ſo confirmed alſo by theſe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances, as the meaneſt handicrafts man on earth ignorant of all policy may eaſily iudge that this promiſe of the Lord Willughby was rather the cloſe and period of all this buſineſſe, referring it ſelfe to the precedent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5766:13"/> treaty. Before that treaty a man may well iudge by theſe occurrents, that things could not haue beene ſo reduced, and how it might haue beene afterward compaſſed, let men iudge by that which followeth. The Lord Willughby then, vpon his entry into the towne hauing by Gods good grace, conducted th'af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to this point, &amp; being no leſſe deſirous to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue this courſe of his ſincere actions, cauſed the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours to reſtore to the Magiſtrat and burgers of the towne their armes, a poinct yet not mentioned in the treaty, and ſo being called away for hir Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>August</label> he went from thence about the eight of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt to Haghe, for the continuall ſetting forward by his preſence, as much as in him might lie, the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the counſaile of Eſtate. But the doubt of Berghen op Zoom and Oſtend not yet being ouer paſt but encreaſing rather, becauſe the Spaniſh fleete drew neere, it was thought good that his Lordſhip ſhould tranſport preſently to Middleburgh, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing order to thoſe two townes as neede ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Now forſomuch as in ſuch caſes it is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary point to haue men of warre, and the rather for that hir Maieſtie had already ſent for 1000. ſoldiours into England vnder the leading of Colonel Morgan; the Lord Willughby forthwith about the 15 of this moneth of Auguſt, ſent for 200 horſes from Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh to be emploied as neede ſhould fal out. And by many aduertiſements in diuerſe places, their was great apparance that thoſe 200 horſe would haue come forth of the garriſon. But vpon newes that the Lord our God had giuen hir Maieſty victory againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5766:14"/> the better part of the Spaniſh fleete, and that the reſt were chaſed Northward, the garriſon eſteeming the great danger to be well ouer, began to excuſe by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the 17. of Auguſt, alleaging certein difficulties yet to be diſcuſſed betweene them and the towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, namely an oth of fidelity from the burgers for aſſurance of the towne and themſelues, which once done they would be commanded any where either for ſeruice of hir Maieſtie or of the vnited Prouinces of the Low countries. While theſe things paſſed, the Lord Willughby ſeing Oſtend quit from an immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſiege by ouerthrow of the Spaniards, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>September</label> tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Middelburgh to Berghen op Zoom in the beginning of September, from whence he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed Count Maurice of Naſſau of certaine intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that Gertrudenbergh was not yet aſſured through ſome ielous feare in the ſoldiours (for feare of puniſhment euermore tormenteth th'offendor) &amp; that therfore it were good there to ſtabliſh a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of warre for recouering in of the ſoldiours by litle and litle, otherwiſe the towne would certeinly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a denne of freebuters. Now if after theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents &amp; aduertiſements, Count Maurice of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau and the States eſtabliſhed there no counſaile of warre, they muſt impute it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; the rather for that not one of them during nor ſince the treaty, would or durſt euer to this day once looke into the towne, not ſo much as to accompany and aſſiſt the Lord Willughby in this waighty affaire, nor yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward by courteous conuerſation &amp; enterteinment to bring the garriſon out of this ielous feare, and to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5766:14"/> induce them to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue a towne ſo much importing religion and all the country. What could the Lord Willughby do more for bringing a good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into the towne then before his departure to cauſe the ſoldiours (though no ſuch matter were in the treaty) to reſtore to the Magiſtrat and Burghers their armes againe? what could he do more then call foorth 200 horſes as vpon ſo good occaſion he did? Verily theſe three things thus falling out, who would doubt of his dutie and not hold it aſſured?</p>
            <p>The placcat maketh mention of certaine powlder, whereunto we anſwere ſhortly that it was neuer vſed in hir Maieſties ſeruice, but withdrawen to the profit of the States and the country, one part during Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen op Zoom beſieged, &amp; the other part in Zeland. The ſubſtance of that which remaineth may be ſaid in few wordes.</p>
            <p>The Duke of Parma, being diſappointed of his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in Flanders vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the Spaniſh fleete wel beaten, he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſieged Berghen op Zoom with ſo puiſſant an army as for many yeares before he had not the like, where the Lord Willughby was engaged, from the 24 of this September vntill the 13 of Nouember, incluſiuely following. AT the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this ſiege his Lordſhip thought good to ſend for 100. of foote men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gertrudenbergh to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of Berghen op Zoom. But they made difficulty to come aſwell for that th'enemy lay neere them, as alſo for the iuſt feare they had, leaſt they ſhould not be permitted to returne after the ſiege leuied (which yet ſhould haue beene a breach of the contract with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5766:15"/> them) by reaſon whereof his Lordſhip was faine to promiſe them free returne. By theſe ſoldiours which were the beſt trained in all the troupes, and other ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours ſent for from Oſtend, Vliſſing and Briel, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>October</label> and ſpecially by the ſuccours which it pleaſed hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to ſend thither in October, the towne was defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The placcat ſaith in this part, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>November</label> that Count Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau with ſome of the Deputies of the States about the beginning of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, did put the Lord Willughby in remembrance of his promiſe, that accordingly he would bring the towne into the Countes handes. What needed ſuch haſty remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of a thing, which hitherto (as appeereth by al former occurrences) could not haue poſſibly beene done? And now in the time of Berghen beſieged, what apparance was their of bringing it to paſſe, or what reaſon to demaund it? euen now, I ſay, when Count Maurice of Naſſau with the deputies of the generall States, &amp; the counſell of Eſtate lay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their gard in defence of the country of Terthole, &amp; might looke vpon th'enemy in his campe before Berghen, within which the Lord Willughby was faſt ſhut vp, &amp; the better part of hir Maieſties forces with him. Al men of ſobre iudgement will reckon thoſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers vnſeaſonable, when, to attempt it, was to ſuffer the loſſe of Berghen op Zoom, withall incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences thereon depending, and yet with great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualty of effecting ought at Gertrudenbergh. Well, God almighty ſo diſpoſing all things for conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of both theſe townes for this time, as th'enimy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew his artillery by night fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the North dike, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5766:15"/> the deputies of the counſell of Eſtate, and of the States of Holland and Zeland to paſſe ouer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thole to Berghen op Zoom, (for by th'enimies artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery withdrawne the riuer of Volſemer was freed) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom the chiefe were, M. Iames Valcke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailor of Eſtate, M. Iaſpar Vosberghe counſailor of Holland, &amp; M. Iohn Barneuelt aduocat of the States of Holland, who were right welcome to the Lord Willughby, not onely for their ſpeciall degrees and places which they held but alſo for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming as good ſignes of ſome more liberty like to be now, that th'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies artillery was caried away, in which reſpect they paſſed their dinner at the Court of the Lord Willughby in ioility &amp; harty cheere. In this doubtful time, the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of our buſineſſe then in hand requiring no new matter to be ſet abroach which might call vs from thinking how to take order by all meanes ſtill to reſiſt that ſiege continued, the campe not riſing from Berghen op Zoom till ten daies after, yet needes muſt Berneuelt at any hand that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone make great complaints againſt Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, alleging that during this ſiege they had taken certeine marchandiſes going for the country of the enimy, by name for Breda, Roſendale &amp; other places thereabouts, and which had paid all rights due for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which taking of theirs becauſe it was an offence againſt a reſolution and ordinance of the States ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the garriſon muſt therefore be well puniſhed according to their fault. And forſomuch as they could not be eaſily puniſhed (as he ſaid) except the towne might come to the States hands, he therefore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5766:16"/> deſired the Lord Willughby to remember his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and his Lordſhip not hauing leiſure to breath from continuall reſiſting, th'enimies army ſtill being before Berghen, he muſt forthwith bethinke how to bring Gertrudenbergh into the Counts hands, or els (ꝙ Barneuelt) I know how otherwiſe to bring it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the States, proteſting that he rather wiſhed Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudenbergh to fall into th'enimies hands then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in that caſe. Theſe indiſcreet wordes vttered with lowde ſpeech in great chaufe of choler and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, comming to the ſoldiours eares of the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Gertrudenbergh, whereof there were, as you haue heard, one hundred in the towne of Berghen op Zoom, it was no neede to bid them to make haſt home to their garriſon ſo ſoone as euer th'enemy had raiſed his campe, neither could all the offices and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements of the Lord Willughby ſtay them, his Lordſhip hauing in truth, loſt all his former intereſt, credit, and wonted power of perſuaſion with them, by meanes of this kinde of broad ſpeech from Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelt, &amp; hauing now no other way but faire meanes to vſe toward them, becauſe before their comming out from Gertrudenbergh thither, they were promiſed a free returne.</p>
            <p>Th'enimy raiſing campe from Berghen the 13 of Nouember, as is ſaid, the Lord Willughby tooke or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for that which was to be done after the ſiege, and tranſported him ſelfe to Dort, where ſir Iohn Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field who alſo had bene ſomewhile at Berghen in the ſiege, came to ſee his Lordſhip the 19 of this moneth, and told him that the ſoldiours of Gertrudenbergh
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5766:16"/> for more part were vpon point of an other mutine, by reaſon of Barneuelts lowd &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeech at Berghen, being ſuch (ſaid they) as they perceiued they were not ſincerely and plainly treated withall in Iuly laſt, &amp; therefore ſith, by Barneuelts ſpeech, it ſeemed that the States pretended to recouer into their hands the towne of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, belike, to thruſt in another garriſon, they would on the other ſide aduiſe for their owne ſurety. The Lord Willughby hearing this, ſent backe S. Iohn Wingfield to Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſwell for preuention of all inconueniences likely to fall by his abſence, as alſo to declare to that garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that they ſhould do well to giue no heede to ſuch ſpeeches, but to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue their good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and, as for his Lordſhip, he would endeuour no thing more hartily with the States then to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by all meanes whatſoeuer might ſerue to th'ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the treaty. Thus much being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by ſir Iohn Wingfield, though it were very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the ſoldiours, yet ceaſed they not by faire words to win away the Burgers armes, for their aſſurance &amp; ſafety, as they ſaid. For, the offendor ſtill caſteth all backe reckonings. Some taking pleaſure to ſpeake euill, go no further then theſe termes of the placcat, and ſeeing this conference at Dort, are not aſhamed to ſay againſt a direct truth, that all this was by former conſent of the Lord Willughby. But all the world may ſee the vanitie of this abuſe, by his Lordſhips letter of the 25 of this Nouember, ſharply blaming there former attempt, with expreſſe commandement on hir Maieſties behalfe to render
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5766:17"/> the armes before taken from the burghers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto if they obeied not, the fault muſt be laid vpon Barneuelts brauing ſpeeches at Berghes, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſuch doubtfull feares in thoſe ſoldiors braines as cauſed all this miſchief following.</p>
            <p>And if we had not thus euidently where to lay this fault, yet all men of good and ſound iudgement know you may not pike theſe quarels at other men by ſuch extrauagant preſumptions &amp; circumſtances, who by better proofes ſetting forth the truth can cleere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For to proceede by circumſtances and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might euen ſo iudge that Barneuelt (whoſe ſignature was th'aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tike warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to paſſe this placcat) were the greateſt traitor in the land, becauſe ſome will not let to ſay that he wrote to Richardot preſident of the Duke of Parmas counſaile of Eſtate, that he the ſame Barneuelt would ſo carie the affaires of the States of the vnited Prouinces in the Low countries, that they ſhould fall into the hands of the King of Spaine. And could any man wiſh a better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>currence of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances or more euident proofe, then the ſelfe ſame way that he taketh? to wit, to drawe drie the threſors of thoſe Prouinces already ſo farre in arrerages, and all to leuy ſecretely an army wherewith to aſſaile by water and land a towne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated with the generality, bringing to the bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery all the beſt ſoldiours of that country. A man may eaſily iudge by what faithfull and martiall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe the men of warre of that country, left their trenches to th'enimy before Gertrudenbergh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raſed nor throwne downe, as alſo vpon what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5766:17"/> Count Maurice of Naſſau might not be ſuffered to accord with the garriſon of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, when the miniſter of the Church there &amp; the Schoute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching mercy, offered to Count Maurice reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conditions on the part of the towne and garriſon. Wherfore would not Barneuelt accept thoſe offers, except it were thereby to do th'enimy good ſeruice, and therewithall alſo to be aduenged of Dort where he hath borne and doth beare a particular hatred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that town did euer greatly reſpect the Queene and could neuer approue all th'actions of ſome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues deputies to the States of Holland, &amp; leaſt of all did Dort allow this raſh ſiege moſt vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly enterpriſed and performed. On the other ſide, experience now ſheweth, what a ſpeciall piece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice Barneuelt did to the Spaniſh king, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by open ſpeach in publique aſſemblies ſundry times to certeine miniſters of the Goſpell, deputies for the Church of Holland in ſommer 1587. that it was a great abuſe &amp; moſt pernicious errour to thinke that the vnited Prouinces were not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly able, in richeſſe, and puiſſance, to mainteine, conſerue and defend themſelues againſt the common enimy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neede of ſuccours from the Queene, or any other Princes aide in the world. This vaine counſaile brought all that country into a terrible confuſion &amp; mutinery of ſoldiours, bereuing it of all authority, counſaile, leaders, ſoldiours and mony, making it a contempt to all neighbours. Euery politique man then may iudge Barneuelts deedes to agree well with his letters. Likewiſe Greffier Cornelius Aerſſens,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5766:18"/> who ſigned this placcat, being heretofore exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and atteinted of treaſon, and thereupon ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from his office and reſtrained to his houſe in Vtrecht, for writing and holding correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy with th'enimy, namely with the Magiſtrat of Bruxels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing him ſeruice and friendſhip, we ſhall not need more particularly to diſcourſe after what ſort he had before that time ſent his wife ſecretly to Antwerpe carrying an other womans name for laying of the better fundation to all his correſpondence, with ſuch a paſport as to that end he him ſelfe had diſpatched and ſigned.</p>
            <p>Now to go to the offer made by Sir Iohn Norris, and the comming of M. Bodley counſailor of Eſtate in the Low countries, which the placcat me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioneth; firſt you muſt vnderſtand that thoſe two perſons for the places which they held, if they could aduance the matter of Gertrudenbergh, it was either by force or faire meanes, by deedes or by wordes. As for any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement by faire meanes, it is already ſhewed to how litle purpoſe that had bene, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that though the garriſon was content to giue ſome eare, yet tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Barneuelts brauing former ſpeeches they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue truſt or credit vnto any thing propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, making full accompt that we went about to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap them, as the ſaid Lord Ambaſſadour found by experience, when he thought to haue drawen from them ſome ſoldiours for Portugal ſeruice, according to ſuch counſaile and aduiſe as the Lord Willughby had before giuen to that effect. To bring any thing there to paſſe by force, was not thought good during
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5766:18"/> the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which yet had it ſeemed good, could not haue bin done during the ſiege before Berghe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> op zoo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the reaſons already ſpoken of. After th'enemy gone from Berghen op Zoom, to go againſt Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh with the ſoldiors hauing endured the ſiege togither with thoſe others which had lien abroad in Tertholen beaten with raine and wether, was a thing neuer propounded, the ſaid Ambaſſador neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring any charge from hir Maieſtie for beſieging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny towne confederated with the generality, but for gathering a certeine proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoldiors according to his enſtructions for the ſeruice of Portugal. <note place="margin">Wach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>donck.</note> And had he had other charge, as he had not, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>December</label> yet the Duke of Parmas ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe (after th'enimy gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Berghen op Zoom) being before Wachtendonck vntill the ſame loſt about the 27 of December, did ſet them a worke ſo as there was no leiſure to ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gertrudenbergh, though they would neuer ſo faine haue forced it. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally when after S. Iohn Norris departure they aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gertrudenbergh not making the Lord Willugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by of their counſaile but by all meanes concealing it from him, and (which is more) without the priuity &amp; counſaile of the counſaile of Eſtate, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quite againſt the treaty with hir Maieſtie, we ſee to our griefe how well they ſped.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>January, 1589</label> To proceed to the moneth of Ianuary 1589 fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, certeine complaints comming to the Lord Willughby concerning contributions out of the country of Breda belonging to the Princeſſe of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge, about which they of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh were ſaid to demeane themſelues ſomewhat inordinately: his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5766:19"/> Lordſhip forthwith ſent thither one of his folke able to redreſſe th'abuſe if any there were, and therein was ſo much done, as not onely all complaints ceaſed, but the Princeſſe had, to hir deſire and contentment, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all goods remaining at Gertrudenbergh ſince Count Hohenlos gouernment. What could the Lord Willughby do more for all parts? well, the placcat ſaith on, that the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh ſeing the contributions, which they dealt with, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſed not for their pay, and that (according to their treaty) the time of their compt and reckoning for ſatisfaction of that which wanted, drew neere, to wit, February following: they gat certeine Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats of the towne to go to the Haghe, to ſignifie from them all this matter to the States generall and counſaile of Eſtate, for ſome conuenient order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The Magiſtrates ſo endeuored as the 25 of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they obteined for the garriſon a good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſolution. That is to ſay, in effect, that the States &amp; counſaile of Eſtate of the vnited Prouinces of the Low countries inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to giue reaſonable ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gertrudenbergh, within ten daies after the firſt ſix moneths which ſhould expire the 15 of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary following. Likewiſe Count Maurice of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau by the 27 of the ſame moneth, ſent them worde that they ſhould haue all maner reaſonable content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Lord Willughby in this meane while ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a iourny to Vliſſing, and after his returne falling into ſome infirmity, gaue neuertheleſſe continually the beſt order that could be (for performing hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties commandements and the countties ſeruice)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5766:19"/> to tranſport for England one after an other the ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours appointed to the Portugal voiage, and ſpecially the horſemen remaining. This buſineſſe almoſt all diſpatched, it pleaſed hir Maieſtie to honor him with hir letters of permiſſion to come home into England for ſome ſhort while, according to his long ſute for the ſame. In which letters hir Maieſtie ſignifying a care that the matter of Gertrudenbergh ſhould be diſcretely ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>February</label> the L. Willughby cauſed thereof an extract tranſlated into French to be deliuered to the generall States the 18 of February together with certeine memorials from him ſelfe to that purpoſe, praying that it would pleaſe the States general to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe how that garriſon might be ſomewhat conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, offering his owne ſeruice in that behalfe, with more ample declaration, that in that ſeruice, togither with ſuch as might pleaſe them to depute of their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly and of the counſaile of Eſtate, he would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy him ſelfe as zealouſly, ſincerely, and affectionat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he had euer done in ſeruice of hir Maieſtie and that country. Hereto it pleaſed not the States to vouchſaue any anſwere at all, though a matter mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring good cauſe of contentment to them, for hir Maieſties princely deſire &amp; good wil ſhewed therby, as alſo to employ the Lord Willughby, who for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying hir Maieſties commandements and his owne dutie, offered his ſeruice: the rather for that in Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paſt they had already reſolued to ſatisfie that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in ſome reaſonable ſort. Well, not receiuing any anſwere, he wrote his ſecond memorials to the ſame ende the 21 following. Whereunto he was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5766:20"/> anſwered by way of apoſtille (quite contrary to the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the 25 of Ianuary paſt) that the deputies of the generall States had none authority from there ſuperiours to deale with the garriſon of Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, and that ſo much the leſſe as the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby had not (ſaid they) performed his promiſe of bringing the towne to Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maurices ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, without which the country was not to pay this ſumme ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do greater ſeruice to hir Maieſtie &amp; the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: not leauing out in this reſolution ſuch abuſes as had paſſed in that towne. To this apoſtille the Lord Willughby anſwered ſummarily, how the treaty of Gertrudenbergh had paſſed from the beginning to th'end, making good proofe alſo that therein he had beene not the alone actor but a third perſon, warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by diuers commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to accord them, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his comming betweene would neuer haue agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe things were come to ſuch extremity for want of paiment which the States ought to haue made in time and place. In which emploiment no more then in any other, his Lordſhip proued that he neuer receiued any thing from them to induce this promiſe, but was ſo farre from making any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe before the contract with Gertrudenbergh, that quite contrary, it was long after, as appeeres by the very words thereof making expreſſe relation to that former promiſe of Count Maurice of Naſſau to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gertrudenbergh at the treaty making for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their liues, wiues and children. His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip farther ſet foorth in this anſwere, the offices he had doone in reforming th'abuſes befallen in that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5766:20"/> towne ſo often as euer they came to his eare.</p>
            <p>This reſolution of the States cutting of all hope of there further treaty with Gertrudenbergh, yet to preuent the apparant breach and vtter diſunion, if that garriſon ſhould come to any inckling of that which had thus paſſed, and to leaue nothing vndone for accompliſhing all the good pleaſures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of hir Maieſtie his Miſtriſſe, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip made his iourney for England by the way of Gertrudenbergh. Where finding them in reaſonable diſpoſition, expecting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment according to the reſolution of the 25 of Ianuary, he by nouriſhing this their hope, brought them ſo farre on (notwitſtanding the ielouſie they had conceiued of him) that by his perſuaſion they promiſed vnder their hands, to giue ouer all medling with contributions and publique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues, aſwell within their towne as in the country adioining, thereby preuenting all farther complaints and making manifeſt to hir Maieſtie and all others, that they ſought not to be maiſters of the generall contributions and other reuenues, but rather deſired one or two threſurers to be appointed for recept thereof, allowing them but there compt and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from ſix moneths to ſix moneths according to the treaty, as appeereth by their originall declaration giuen to the L. Willughby to be ſignified to hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie that ſhe might be pleaſed to giue notice therof to Dort their next neighbour, becauſe they coueted nothing but good neighbourhood &amp; amitie with all. Theſe things thus well brought about, the L. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby being well apaid to haue holden the matters
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5766:21"/> in ſo moderate termes, tooke ſhip from Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh to Midleburgh in Zela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about the 3 of March, from whence after order giuen for ſome things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning onely the Engliſh nation, his Lordſhip went to Vliſſing to embarke for England. But while he ſtaid there for a good wind, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">month </seg>March</label> tidings came the 15 of March that Count Maurice of Naſſau &amp; the States had beſieged Gertrudenbergh. The Lord Willugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by could but wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der at it, &amp; wrote expreſly to Count Maurice of Naſſau that ſith he purpoſed thus to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege the towne, he might yet haue giuen him ſome litle watchword that ſo he might haue withdrawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brother in law and ſiſter there, which thing to do his Lordſhip had many times heretofore offered, aſwell in particular as to the States generals themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming away fro the Haghe. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Lordſhips letters, on went the ſiege, and that with great extremities quite againſt the treaty of the 26 and 27 of Iuly paſſed and the generall pardon thereupon: yea without any regard of their owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the 25 of Ianuary laſt, whereby they had promiſed to that garriſon reaſonable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally not ſuffering their hardned hartes to be entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Chriſtian beſeechings &amp; lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table teares of the Miniſter of the goſpell there, &amp; of the Schout which were ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the towne to make ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for mercy and pitie, ſo fell the towne moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily into the hands of the Duke of Parma.</p>
            <p>By this iournall manage of matters &amp; by theſe alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and probations, we truſt that as in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of all men it may be moſt truly ſaid, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5766:21"/> boaſt on the part of the Lord Willughby that next after God, vnder the name of hir Maieſtie &amp; the princely reſpect wherein ſhe is holden, the towne of Gertrudenbergh had beene ſo many moneths kept through his Lordſhips trauaile and good offices: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo we may hope that theſe worſt ſpeakers of him, now ſeeing the truth diſcloſed, will let the blame of this great loſſe reſt vpon them that were cauſers of it. And ſo much the rather becauſe ſuch as were then in Gertrudenbergh do ſay that during the ſiege, the ſo much vrged promiſe of the Lord Willughby, was ſent in to the beſieged from th'aſſailants, with a falſe date later then the originall, as if one would haue done a thing for the nonce to prouoke them to yeeld the towne to th'enimy. And leaſt this our often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the generall States of the vnited prouinces in the Low countries, ſhould be miſenterpreted to any derogation of their reputation, honour and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: all Princes, States, Lords, Gentlemen, Counſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Magiſtrates, &amp; all perſons in particular of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer qualitie, eſtate or condition, are moſt humbly praied and deſired with all reuerence and inſtance, not to conceiue, by occaſion of this diſcourſe, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion then right good of the generall States of thoſe prouinces lawfully aſſembled, nor yet, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion hereof, once to ſpeake otherwiſe then wel and right honorably either of themſelues in generall or particular, or yet of their actions or comportements. For, the purpoſe of this diſcourſe is chiefly to touch the ſlanders and ſlanderous inſinuations of the plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat againſt the Lord Willughby. As for the caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5766:22"/> the States &amp; the garriſon of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, as we meane nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to determine or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it, but leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be iudged according as they deſerue, euen ſo do we not purſue the placcat for the diſproportionable and vile valuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Engliſh Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Capteins, &amp; Soldiours there with the reſt, by a few more or leſſe gildres or Florins: neither for the iniquity thereof in proclaiming and banning them to death vniudged &amp; vnheard, not ſo much as ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them who in an equall court are ready to come in to anſwer, &amp; therfore can not be ſaid contumaces or refuſing to be iuſtified: nor yet for the inhumanity thereof, in expoſing them to the violence of euery bloody hand: nor yet for the barbariſme thereof, in prouoking and rewarding ſuch perilous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſions &amp; priuat violences; beſides other vntruths, impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp; diſorders more like to come out of ſome Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh veſſell of the ſame humor with him that penned the Turkiſh Bann againſt the late right worthy Prince of Orenge, then to paſſe with the conſent of th'ono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable States generall in a iuſt aſſembly, or to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in any other Chriſtian court. This were a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour apart. We will leaue theſe wrongs to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and almighty iudge of the world, whom we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech on behalfe of the States to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch grace and fauour as by their owne proper forces with th'aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of their good neighbors, they may be hable to mainteine their ſtate, to th'aduancement of Chriſts Goſpell and th'enlargement of his Church Sobeit.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="references">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5766:22"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT OF COMMISSIONS, ordonnances, letters, inſtructions, aduertiſements, intelligences and other ſuch warrants, extant to be giuen in euidence for proofe of the principall points of this diſcourſe, whereto they bin reſpectiuely quoted, page &amp; line.</head>
            <div type="list_of_orders">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 6. Line 3.</note> 1 A Commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpatched the 7 of April 1588. ſtil. nou. authoriſing the Magiſtrats of Dort, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point th'alteration at Gertrudenbergh, becauſe the garriſon there would not in any ſort treat w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th the States.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 11.</note> 2 Letters from the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh the 20 of April 1588, declaring they would no haue communication with any ſaue with the Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby in behalfe of hir moſt excellent Maieſtie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 12.</note> 3 A letter from the Magiſtrat of Dort the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of April 1588, that the ſame garriſon would common with none, ſaue with the Lord Willughby hir M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Lieutenant in th'vnited prouinces of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w countries.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 13.</note> 4 A letter fro the Magiſtrat of Gertrudenbergh, of the ſame date and tenor.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 6.</note> 5 Letters from Count Hohenlo of the laſt of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril, requiring the Lord Willughby to deale in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the ſame alteration, for preuenting th'en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies driftes and practiſes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 26.</note> 6 A letter of the Lord Willughby the 7 of May 1588, requiring the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh to ſend deputies to Dort according to a ſiufconduct for that purpoſe diſpatched, for further declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5766:23"/> Lordſhip of their demand and meaning.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 31.</note> 7 A letter from the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh the 8. of May, for excuſe of deputies to be ſent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Lordſhip to come perſonally thither for the better appointment of things vpon the place.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 7. Line 2.</note> 8 Letters of crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the L. Willughby the 9 of May, for Sir Iohn Wingfield, M. Thomas Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, M. George Gilpin &amp; the deputies of Dort, ſent to Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh to perſuade them to ſend deputies to Dort notwithſtanding their former refuſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 12.</note> 9 Articles exhibited to the L. Willugbby by the dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tes of the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh after their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>riuall at Dort, concerning their aſſurance.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 11.</note> 10 A diſcourſe of the reaſons of the alteration of the ſoldiours in garriſon at Gertrudenbergh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 15.</note> 11 Th'apoſtilles giuen vpon the former articles by the L. Willughby with aduiſe of the Magiſtrat of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt, where among other things, that garriſon is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arply blamed for demanding pay from hir Maieſtie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> whom they neuer yet had done any ſeruice in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cular.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 10. Line 7.</note> 12 Letters of very louing thankes from Count Maurice of Naſſau to the Lord Willughby the 11 of May vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> particular aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſame Count by M. George Gilpin, of euery thing paſſed. Wherby appeereth that the reproch of the placcat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the apoſtilles of the 9 of May is far fro the purpoſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 8. Line 30.</note> 13 The demand of the ſoldiors of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh by writing of the 14 of May for 31 moneths pay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſing the reſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 11. Line 2.</note> 14 Letters from Count Maurice of Naſſau the 29
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5766:23"/> of May to the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh, declaring that the ſame towne after death of his Lord and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Honorable memory, apperteineth to him and his brothers and ſiſters who had neuer offended that garriſon, and therefore deſired commiſſioners from thence for better vnderſtanding of their meaning.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 16.</note> 15 A commiſſion from the generall States the 2 of Iune 1588, to treat with the garriſon of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 17.</note> 16 A commiſſion from the States of Holand the 3. of Iune 1588, to appoint th'alteration of the ſame garriſon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 12. Line 8.</note> 17 A letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Iohn Wingfield the 10 of Iune to Count Maurice of Naſſau, aduertiſing very parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly the ſtate of Gertrudenbergh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 22.</note> 18 A letter from Count Maurice of Naſſau the 11 of Iune, requiring the L. Willughby to haſten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from Oſtend for appointing th'alterat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on at Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, for ſo much as it would not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 14.</note> 19 A letter from the Magiſtrat of Dort the 19 of Iune, aduertiſing the Lord Willughby the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Walc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerland about the affaires of Vere, &amp;c. that the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diors of Gertrudenbergh would giue ouer to th'ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, except his Lordſhip ſtaied it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 22.</note> 20 A letter from the States of Holland the 20 of Iune, praying the Lord Willughby, that leauing all buſineſſe he would approch as neere Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh as he could, for appointing th'alteration of that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to hir Maieſties contentment.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 24.</note> 21 A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion from the States of Holland the 27 of Iune, to promiſe 200000. florins or 20 months
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5766:24"/> wages to the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 13. Line 5.</note> 22 A letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the L. Willughby the 29 of Iune, ſharply reprouing that garriſon for refuſing the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſumme.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 15. Line 17.</note> 23 Inſtruction for M. Richard Allen an Engliſh gentleman and for commiſſary Matrut the 9 of Iuly 1588, being ſent by the Lord Willughby, at requeſt of the States to let the garriſon at Gertrudenbergh vnderſtand, that they ſhould be ſatisfied with in fewe daies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 16. Line 4.</note> 24 The contract made with them of Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e 26 &amp; 27 of Iuly by the L. Willughby in the name of hir Maieſtie and of Count Maurice of Naſſau in preſence of the deputies of the States.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 17. Line 25.</note> 25 A letter from the Lord Willughby the 28 of Iuly, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiring the counſell of Eſtate to beſtow the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Gertrudenbergh vpon Colonel Sche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 18. Line 7.</note> 26 A letter from the Lord Willughby the 28 of Iuly, aduertiſing Count Maurice that the ſoldiors of Gertrudenbergh would not be ſatisfied without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one cornet of 200 lances, and one of 100 carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, one company of 200 foote, &amp; an other of 150.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 15 and 24.</note> 27 Letters fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Count Maurice of Naſſau the 28 &amp; 29 of Iuly, referring the reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of th'aforeſaid companies to the Lord Willughbies diſcretion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 19. Line. 15.</note> 28 Two draughts of an oth ſent to Count Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau, by reaſon the garriſon of Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh made difficultie at the name of the States.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 20.</note> 29 A letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Count Maurice of Naſſau the laſt of Iuly, allowing the name of the States to be left out in the foreſaid oth, according to the chaunge
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5766:24"/> which was made thereof, &amp; therewithall aduertiſing that the States thought not good to beſtow the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Gertrudenbergh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Colonel Schenk.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 20. Line 11.</note> 30 Letters fro the Lord Willughby of the 2.3.5. and 6. of Auguſt to the counſell of Eſtat, to Count Maurice of Naſſau, to the States of Holland, and to the Magiſtrat of Dort, to ſupply the mony wanting for pay.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 24.</note> 31 A general pardon fro Count Maurice of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau the 28 of Iuly, for all things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh during the alteration.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 21. Line 10.</note> 32 An act of the laſt of Iuly, wherein Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Naſſau &amp; the States of Holland, do giue great thankes to the Lord Willughby for his trauailes in appeaſing the ſame alteration.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 22. Line 1.</note> 33 The Lord Willughbies promiſe to deliuer Gertrudenbergh to Count Maurice when it ſhould lie in his power, ſo as the Count would likewiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which he had promiſed to the garriſon there, for ſauing their liues, wiues and children accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hir Maieſties deſire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 23. Line 25.</note> 34 A letter from the Lord Willughby the 15 of Auguſt, ſending for 200 horſe from Gertrudenbergh to be emploied vpon all occaſions while the Spaniſh fleet was looked for.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 24. Line 15.</note> 35 A letter from the Lord Willughby the 4 of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber aduertiſing Count Maurice that the towne was not aſſured, and that therefore it was conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſtabliſh there a counſell of warre, for reducing the ſoldiours by litle and little to ſome more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order.</item>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5766:25"/>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 29. Line 29.</note> 36 A letter from the Lord Willughby the 25 of Nouember, reprouing the garriſon of Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh for taking away the Burghers armes there, the tenor wherof is ſet in the end hereof tranſlated word for word.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 34. Line 17.</note> 37 The reſolution of the generall States the fiue and twentith of Ianuary 1589, promiſing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the garriſon within ten daies after the ten mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths which ſhould expire in February following, as it is alſo tranſlated in the end hereof.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 25.</note> 38 A letter from Count Maurice of Naſſau the 27 of Ianuary 1589, promiſing contentment to the ſame garriſon according to the former reſolution.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 35. Line 11.</note> 39 Memorialls preſented by the Lord Willugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the 18 of February 1589, to the States generall praying them to depute ſome of their aſſembly with other of the counſaile of Eſtate, to aduiſe how the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh might be contented for ſix moneths, together with which memorialls his Lordſhip ſent th'extraict of hir Maieſties letter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to deale diſcretely with that garriſon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Line 31.</note> 40 Second memorialls to the ſame effect from the Lord Willughby to the States generall the 21 of February, togither with the States reſolution decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring flatly that they would not treate with that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon for want of authoritie from their ſuperiours, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt their other reſolution of the 25 of the moneth next before.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 36. Line 11.</note> 41 The Lord Willughbies anſwer to that reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the 21 of February exhibited by M. Bodley counſailor of Eſtate, wherein among other things,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5766:25"/> his Lordſhip offered to withdraw Sir Iohn Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field out of Gertrudenbergh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 37. Line 15.</note> 42 A diſcours of the third of March 1589, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh offereth to the Lord Willughby as in hir Maieſties name, to quit all dealing with ſuch contributions as hetherto they haue taken, reſting content to be paid according to the treaty, deſirous alſo to hold all good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and neighbourhood with Dort, beſeeching his Lordſhip thereof to aduertiſe hir Maieſtie as on their behalfe.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5766:26"/>
               <head>A LETTER FROM THE LORD WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lughby to Sir Iohn Wingfield Knight, Gouernour of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh, to the Captaine, Sergeant Maior, Lieutenants, Enſignes, and other ſoldiors there holding garriſon, and to euery of them.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 29. Line 29.</note> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Vnderſtand, to my great griefe, that not manydaies paſt, vſing hir Maieſties name and authority, you cauſed the Burghers of the towne of Gertrude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bergh to yeeld vp their armes, without telling them any reaſons leading you thereto. Whereat as hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Lieutenant in theſe partes I can not merueile e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. For if that had beene hir Roiall pleaſure, no doubt, holding the place I do in theſe countries, ſhe would haue ſignified ſo much to me. But ſo far were you of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing any right or reaſon to vſe hir name or authority, that I am ſure hir Maieſtie knoweth it not. And had you had commiſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir to attempt ſuch a matter, yet neuertheleſſe ought you not to haue enterpriſed it of your ſelues without making me firſt &amp; formoſt priuy, both for that I am hir Maieſties Lieutenant here, and alſo your Gouernour choſen and eſtabliſhed according to your oth to me in that quality taken. Now for my part I do not nor euer will allow this deede of yours committed vtterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my priuity, and for the which you can not but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre hir Maieſties high diſpleaſure, ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that heretofore I openly ſignified by Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Gilpin that hir Maieſties will was to haue you hold your ſelues in good accord, ſtreight correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5766:26"/> and ſound friendſhip with your towneſmen, aſwell for aduancement of the common weale as for the weale of that towne. What if ſome Burghers had committed ſome offence, your part had beene to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe me, that knowing the cauſe I might haue ſet downe puniſhment, according to right and by lawful meanes. And therein as you ſhould haue found me moſt ready to do reaſon to euery party, ſo would I not in any wiſe haue ſuffered the good and loiall men louers of their country, inhabiting there and bearing armes theſe many yeares for loue to religion, to their country &amp; for preſeruation of that towne, to receiue ſuch a ſhame as to haue their armes taken away for th'abuſe (if any ſuch were) of ſome particular perſon. I therefore do earneſtly require you and in regard of my place do giue order expreſly that vpon ſight hereof, you ſatisfie the Burghers there, reſtoring to euery towne dweller his armes, leaſt hir Maieſtie may haue iuſt cauſe againſt you for not enough reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting theſe my commandements. But truſting veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that you will not let things runne ſo farre out, but rather take ſome way by gentle meanes to ſeeke hir Maieſties fauour, and ſo meete with all inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that might befall, I beſeech God to giue all and euery of you wiſedome and diſcretion to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme well the ſeruices of hir Maieſtie, and of theſe countries.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Dordrecht <date>the fiue and twentith of Nouember. 1588.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:5766:27"/>
               <head>A Reſolution of the States Generall, promiſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 34. Line 17.</note> VPon declaration to the States generall, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of Eſtate of the vnited prouinces of the Low countries, by the deputies of the towne of Gertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbergh, in the name of the men of warre on foote &amp; horſe there holding garriſon; for obteining count and reckoning for ſix moneths which they haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by vertue of their new commiſſion: It is reſolued that within ten daies after thoſe ſix moneths expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at the 15 of February next, the counſaile of Eſtate ſhall call before them the Treſurers of the companies and others, that haue receiued and taken the mony appointed for enterteinment of that garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; to th'end that they giuing vp th'accompts and other credible informations of the mony which in theſe ſix moneths they haue receiued and had aſwell by contributions and all other meanes of the ſame towne of Gertrudenbergh &amp; other places adioining vnder the prouince of Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as alſo of ſome villages in Brabant for better vnderſtanding how far that pay during theſe ſix moneths is aduanced by way of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt: that ſo after the reckonings made vp, that may be done which ſhall ſtand with reaſon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>So ſet downe and reſolued in th'aſſembly of the aforeſaid States at Haghe <date>25 of Ianuary. 1589. ſtil. nou.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <hi>Egmont vidit.</hi>
               </closer>
               <closer>By order of the foreſaid States.
<signed>C. Aerſsens.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5766:27"/>
               <head>AN EXTRAICT OF A SECOND reſolution of the ſame States generall vpon ſecond Memorialls ſent by the Lord Willughby touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the garriſon of Gertrudenbergh: This reſolution quite contrary to the former.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 36. Line 1.</note> BVt to enter into any communication &amp;c. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of the prouinces thinke not themſelues au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed by their ſuperiours.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>So ſet downe at Haghe, <date>21. February 1589.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <hi>VVermelo vidit.</hi>
               </closer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By order of the aforeſaid States. C. Aerſsens.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
